Papers of the Stratton Family
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Papers of the Stratton Family
1856-1933
1850-1890
The Stratton Family
BHC-MSS 0033
.2085 linear feet 1 box
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Cynthia and Sherwood Stratton were the parents to Charles S. Stratton, a little person made famous by P.T. Barnum under the stage name of General Tom Thumb. The family was native to Bridgeport, and the papers within offer a glimpse into how the family's most famous son impacted the family's wealth.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased in 1996.
Biography
Sherwood E. and Cynthia Stratton were Bridgeport natives and parents to Charles S. Stratton, later made famous by P.T. Barnum as General Tom Thumb. They had two daughters, Mary E. and Francis Jane; the former was married first to A.S. Bassett and then to James H. Osgood. Francis married Royal Basett, who was the head of the Birmingham Iron Foundry and also a trustee for Francis Janes mother.
Charles S. Stratton (January 4, 1838- July 15, 1883), known as General Tom Thumb, was an entertainer and Bridgeport Conn. native who got his start with P.T. Barnum in 1842. Stratton's parents signed him with Barnum at age 4, as exhibiting those with dwarfism was lucrative at the time. Stratton took quickly to performing, and he entertained audiences worldwide, including nobility such as Queen Victoria. Stratton married fellow performer M. Lavinia Warren and the two had a happy marriage. Stratton's performances brought him renown as a celebrity, perhaps one of the biggest at the time, and he and Warren were able to live comfortably when not working. On July 15, 1883, Stratton suffered a stroke and passed away. He is buried at Mountain Grove Cemetery in Bridgeport, Connecticut, with his wife beside him.
Scope and Content of Collection
Mostly within the collection are wills, deeds, financial arrangements, and estate papers. Included are two wills from Charles himself, including one from 1860 prior to his celebrated marriage to Lavinia Warren. Also within are legal documents and personal papers from Mary Stratton (later Osgood), one of Charles' siblings.
Arrangement
Legal papers are placed first and make up the bulk of the collection. The few pieces that are non-legal are placed at the end. There are no formal series, as the material is too brief to warrant it.
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Thumb, Tom, 1838-1883; Bridgeport, Conn.; Dwarfism; Entertainers; People with disabilities; People with disabilities--United States; People with disabilities and the performing arts
- Inventory
  - Sherwood Stratton, will, April, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Charles S. Stratton, will, 1860-1877; Contains two copies of will dated March 1860 and December 1877 respectively. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Cynthia Stratton, legal papers, 1858-1870 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Estate of Mary (Stratton) Osgood, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Stratton and Basset families legal agreements, 1859-1884 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Copy of requests to probate court in Plymouth, Charles Stratton, 1890-1899; Date is unclear (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Legal papers regarding Charles Stratton’s will, 1920-1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Legal papers, 1880-1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Compositions and poetry by Mary (Stratton) Osgood, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clippings including obituaries and estate sales, 1850-1899 (Box 1, Folder 10)